#### SHUBHANSHU KULSHRESTHA

405-3 Donald Street Winnipeg, Manitoba R3L 2P6 Phone: 204-952-7764 Email: shubhanshu.k@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY**

Diligent data professional with 5+ years of experience in database management, data warehousing, reporting & data analytics. Proficient with various data engineering tools to extract, transform and analyze for driving business solutions. Willing to relocate.

#### **EDUCATION**

## M.Sc. in Computer Science

University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB Sept 2012 - April 2014

#### **Bachelor of Engineering (Information Technology)**

Sagar Institute of Research Technology & Science, Bhopal, India Sept 2007 - July 2011

### **Continuing Education: (via Coursera.com)**

- Essential Design Principles for Tableau
  University of California, Davis- September 2018
- Fundamentals of Visualization with Tableau University of California, Davis- March 2018

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Database Management Systems: SQL Server 2008 R2, 2012,2014,2016, MS Access

**Reporting Tools:** SQL Server Reporting Service (SSRS)

ETL Tool:SQL Server Integration Service (SSIS)

Big Data: Knowledge of Hadoop, HDFS, MapReduce, Pig, Tez, Apache spark, Ambari, Yarn

Data Visualization: Tableau, Power BI

Programming Language: C#, VB. NET, SQL, TSQL, Python (NumPy, Pandas)

IDE: Visual Studios, SQL Server Management Studio, Business Intelligence Development Studio, Jupyter

Version Control: Git

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## People Corporation

**Report and Database Administrator** 

**Department**-Billing and Data Operations

• ETL and System Integration

- Lead Billing & Data Operations team on all database, reporting & data management projects
- Implemented end-to-end ETL solution using SSIS to manage data loading to OLAP databases
- o Experience with scheduling daily data loads using SSIS and SQL Server Agent Jobs
- Extract and load claims data into data warehouse using SSIS and SQL Server for claims tracking report
- Created complex **data and control flows in SSIS** to integrate multiple data sources (billing & accounting system) for operational reports

Winnipeg, Canada

April 2014 - Current

- Experience with SSIS to extract information from various file types (CSV, Excel) and load into data warehouse
- Strong understanding of dimensional data modeling and schemas (star & snowflake schema)
- Developed a desktop application to integrate the claims system with accounting system using .NET, SSIS and SQL Server

## Reporting

- Built and maintain queries, stored procedures, and views, for SSRS reports using SQL and T-SQL
- Expertise in developing ad-hoc & automated parameterized, cross-tab & drill down reports using SSRS
- Developed reports for performance and workload analysis of client service team using SSRS subscriptions
- Gather requirements from account managers & clients for complex billing reports and develop using SSRS with 100% client satisfaction
- o Created and managed standard SSRS subscriptions which generates on monthly basis
- o Manage user access for all reports through the Reporting Manager

#### • Data Analysis- Tableau/Microsoft Excel

- Created insightful dashboards for Billing Manager to analyze monthly claims trend using Tableau
- O Design scatter plot to detect any outlier clients in the billing data set using Tableau
- Designed a dashboard for Billing Manager to analyze monthly claims data received from insurance carriers
- o Identify worst performing products by different regions for one of the Coursera courses using Tableau
- o Analyzed billing data in excel using VLOOKUP's and pivot tables to drive insights and interpret trends

### • Database Administration and Optimization

- o Provided second-tier support to IT team to all the database administration issues
- o Monitored query performance using Activity Monitor on SQL Server Management Studio for optimal speed and efficiency to prevent resource bottleneck
- o Optimized data retrieval from product databases by creating indexes in SQL Server

# Flairsoft Consulting Group SQL Server / SSRS Developer

Bhopal, India

Aug 2011 - May 2012

- o Created and managed SQL objects such as views, procedure, table & functions using SSMS
- Designed SQL script to automatically create data dictionary using T-SQL
- o Implemented database backup policy and monitored it to maintain uniform workload
- Optimized data retrieval from product databases by creating indexes in SQL Server
- Built and maintained queries, stored procedures, tables and views, used for SQL Server Reporting Services (SSRS)

## AWARDS AND CERTIFICATION

- Awarded Best Employee for *Customer Service Excellence* in 2017 for going extra mile in serving client service team
- Successfully completed *Student Leadership Development Program*, with opportunity to organize and present a lecture on Team Work at Student Leadership Conference 2014
- International Graduate Student Entrance Scholarship by University of Manitoba, September 2012